<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="exp"
  docName="draft-lienard-lisp-simplify-bum-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Simplifying BUM forwarding">Simplifying BUM forwarding in LISP based VxLAN fabrics</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-lienard-lisp-simplify-bum-00"/>
   
    <author fullname="Raphael Lienard" initials="R." role="editor" surname="Lienard">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>rlienard@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
   
    <date year="2026" month="1" day="27"/>

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>LISP; deployment</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In a Locator/ID Separation Protocol (LISP) network where 
      EID Layer 2 mobility is enabled between RLOCs as per defined
      in <xref target="I-D.ietf-lisp-eid-mobility"/>, the forwarding of
      overlay Broadcast, Unknown unicast, and link-local Multicast
      (BUM) traffic is achieved either by sending an encapsulated
      unicast copy of the packets to all interested RLOCs or by 
      sending an encapsulated multicast packet to the provider 
      network and letting it do the replication as close as possible
      to the destination RLOCs.</t>

      <t>When using multicast replication, <xref target="I-D.ietf-lisp-eid-mobility"/>
      relies on Protocol Independent Multicast - Any Source Multicast
      (PIM ASM) and the use of Rendezvous Points (RPs) within the
      provider network to discover RLOC participation to a L2VNI.</t>
      
      <t>The role of the underlay is to provide a robust and stable transport
      network that is configured once and rarely touched afterwards.
      Importanty, it should be independent from any overlay networks
      that are dynamic by nature. Although as explained above, there
      is currently a direct dependency between one or several 
      underlaying PIM RP(s) and Layer 2 overlay networks supporting BUM.
      This defeats the principle of isolation.</t>

      <t>This document describes an different approach for BUM traffic
      handling within LISP networks by utilising PIM Source-Specific
      Multicast (SSM) instead of PIM ASM in the provider networks 
      and integrating L2VNI RLOC membership discovery directly into
      the LISP control plane. The outlined approach eliminates the
      need for RPs in provider networks and allow the overlay protocol
      LISP to shape the required underlay PIM SSM multicast trees.</t>
      
      <t>This method ensure dynamic native multicast tree formation
      based on overlay need, reduces the configuration and troubleshooting
      burden on network administrators, ensuring more resilient and streamlined
      BUM traffic forwarding within layer 2 LISP fabrics.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
        <t>The Locator/ID Separation Protocol (LISP) has been instrumental in
        advancing the capabilities of network fabrics by separating endpoint
        identifiers and their location within the network infrastructure.
        However, the facilitation of Broadcast, Unknown unicast, and Multicast
        (BUM) traffic within a LISP-enabled environment, especially when
        layer 2 mobility is a consideration, presents notable challenges.
        Among these is the efficient forwarding of BUM traffic to the relevant
        Router Locators (RLOCs) without inducing unicast replication in the underlay network.</t>

        <t>In the current framework, the forwarding of encapsulated BUM traffic
        within a LISP-based fabric relies heavily on the use of Protocol
        Independent Multicast - Any Source Multicast (PIM ASM) and associated
        Rendezvous Points (RPs) within the provider's network. This
        dependency creates a single point of failure and introduces
        operational complexities due to the potential need for multiple RPs
        and the associated maintenance burden.</t>

        <t>This RFC proposes an alternative method aimed at simplifying BUM
        traffic forwarding by leveraging PIM Source-Specific Multicast (SSM)
        within LISP-based networks that utilize layer 2 Virtual Network
        Identifiers (L2VNI). The approach outlined herein delegates the
        responsibility of multicast source discovery from the provider
        network's underlay to the LISP control plane itself. By integrating
        dynamic (S,G) multicast tree creation triggered by LISP control-plane
        messaging, this solution seeks to reduce the complexity of the
        provider network's role to ensuring basic unicast reachability
        between RLOCs and supporting PIM SSM for multicast routing.</t>

        <t>The scope of this RFC is focused exclusively on LISP networks with
        layer 2 extensions, addressing the specific case of BUM traffic
        forwarding. The document will detail the mechanisms by which the LISP
        control plane can manage multicast source discovery and facilitate
        the establishment of efficient multicast forwarding paths without the
        need for traditional PIM ASM constructs and Rendezvous Points.</t>

        <t>The intended audience for this RFC includes network architects,
        engineers, and administrators tasked with managing LISP-based
        fabrics, particularly those who seek to optimize their networks for
        layer 2 mobility.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Requirements-Language">
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
        RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
        <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
        all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Definition-Terms">
      <name>Definition of Terms</name>
        <t>LISP related terms, notably Map-Request, Map-Reply, Ingress Tunnel
        Router (ITR), Egress Tunnel Router (ETR), Map-Server (MS) and
        Map-Resolver (MR) are defined in the LISP specifications <xref
        target="RFC9300"/> and <xref target="RFC9301"/>.</t>

        <t>Terms defining interactions with the LISP Mapping System are defined
        in <xref target="RFC9301"/>.</t>

        <t>Terms related to the procedures for signal free multicast are defined
        in <xref target="RFC8378"/>.</t>

        <t>The following terms are here defined to facilitate the descriptions
        and discussions within this particular document.</t>

        <t>Site-Overlay - Overlay network at a specific area or domain. This
        overlay network has a dedicated Mapping System.</t>

        <t>Border-xTR - xTR that connects a site-overlay to one or more
        uberlays.</t>

        <t>xTR - LISP Tunnel Router as defined in <xref target="RFC9301"/>. An
        xTR connects end-points to the site-overlay.</t>

        <t>Local Mapping System - Mapping system of the site-overlay</t>

        <t>Uberlay - Overlay network that interconnects different site-overlays
        to each other. The Uberlay has a dedicated Mapping System and creates an
        overlay amongst the border xTRs which connect different
        site-overlays.</t>

        <t>Uberlay Mapping System - Autonomous mapping system dedicated to the
        uberlay.</t>

        <t>Site-Overlay EIDs - Also referred to as local site-overlay EIDs,
        these are the EIDs that are connected to xTRs in a particular
        site-overlay and are registered in their own local site-overlay mapping
        system. These EIDs will also be registered in the uberlay but not in the
        remote site-overlay mapping systems.</t>

        <t>Remote site-overlay EIDs - These are EIDs connected and registered in
        site-overlays other than the local site-overlay.</t>

        <t>Local site-overlay EIDs - These are EIDs connected and registered in
        the local site-overlay.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Working-Principles">
      <name>Working Principles</name>
        <section anchor="Working-Principles_Prerequisites">
          <name>Prerequisites</name>
          <t>Every network devices participating in a common L2VNI MUST use a
          common PIM SSM group in the RLOC space to transport BUM traffic.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Working-Principles_First-Node">
          <name>First network device to join the L2VNI</name>
          <t>When the first network device joins an L2VNI where BUM is allowed,
          it MUST register it’s intent to send and receive multicast traffic
          in the RLOC space for the group that has been assigned to the L2VNI.
          This is done by sending a LISP Map-Register to the LISP Map Server
          containing the Layer2 IID, it’s RLOC address and the PIM SSM Group
          on which the BUM traffic will be mapped. The Map-Server stores a new
          record in the database and triggers a lookup to select all entries
          of the table. A Map-Notify containing (L2IID, Vector[list of all RLOCs present in the L2VNI], Multicast Group)
          MUST be sent to all results of this lookup. In this specific scenario,
          the first joiner will only see it’s own RLOC address in the vector
          list and that will serve as a confirmation that it has join the L2VNI.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Working-Principles_Additional-Node">
          <name>Additional network devices joining the L2VNI</name>
          <t>Following the same process described in 3.1, the network device sends
          a Map-Register to the MS containing the L2IID to join, it’s RLOC 
          address and the PIM SSM Group for BUM transport. At this point,
          the Map Server looks up the database for the provided L2IID and founds
          an existing entry. It adds the new RLOC in the vector list of RLOCs
          participating to the L2VNI and verifies that the PIM SSM group is matching.
          It then sends a Map-Notify (L2IID, Vector[All RLOCs in the L2VNI], Multicast Group)
          to all members of the Vector including the new joiner.</t>

          <t>The new joiner receives a confirmation that it has successfully joined
          the L2VNI by seeing its RLOC in the Vector. It also discover the list
          of all other members of the L2VNI and do a lookup in the MRIB to see
          if a multicast tree already exists to them. Since it is new to the L2VNI,
          no entries should be present and a PIM SSM Join will be sent towards all
          the members to receive the encapsulated BUM traffic from them.</t>

          <t>All others members of the L2VNI receiving the Map-Notify will do the
          same by verifying their own membership. They will also lookup for existing
          multicast tree entries in their MRIB for all other RLOCs present in
          the Vector list. Since the new joiner is not present, they will all
          send a PIM SSM Join to it.</t>

          <t>At this point, a full-mesh of multicast trees should be created between 
          all members of the L2VNI. This allows BUM traffic transport across
          a PIM SSM core network.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Working-Principles_Graceful-leave">
          <name>Graceful leave operations</name>
          <t>When removing a network device gracefully from an L2VNI, it MUST send
          a PIM Leave to all members of the L2VNI. After doing this, a MAP-Register
          MUST be sent to the MAP SERVER containing (L2IID, it’s RLOC, Multicast Group)
          plus a TTL=0 to signal that this record has expired. The MAP SERVER deletes
          the requestor RLOC from Vector list and notifies every one of this change
          by sending a MAP-NOTIFY with a new vector list. All the other Network Devices
          compare the vector list to the MRIB and find out that there is an extra entry
          in the MRIB compared to the Vector list and send a PIM Leave to that RLOC.</t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Optimisations">
      <name>Optimisations</name>
        <section anchor="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees">
          <name>Bidirectional multicast trees</name>
          <t>Depending on the network size, a full mesh of multicast trees
          (between all the RLOC participating to an L2VNI) can create a
          huge number of entries in the MRIB. To reduce this amount, it
          might be beneficial to manipulate the topology to force the
          multicast traffic to pass through a central point.</t>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees_RootNode-Join">
            <name>A root node is joining an L2VNI</name>
            <t>Initially, the Map-Server is rejecting any unflagged MAP-Register
            from network devices willing to join a L2VNI configured with
            a hub-n-spoke topology. A network device that has been configured
            as root (TBD) sends a MAP-Register to the Map-Server with a
            new entry (L2IID, it’s RLOC, Multicast Group) and a special
            Flag (TBD) that identifies itself as root for the tree. The MS
            accept the registration and add a new entry to the DB as
            (L2IID, Vector[RLOC] (with flag set if root), Multicast group).
            The MS sends a MAP-NOTIFY to all devices in the Vector
            (only one is currently in the vector). The Root node can validate
            that it has successfully joined the L2VNI. The MS is now ready to
            accept registrations from other network devices.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees_NonRootNode-Join">
            <name>Non-root nodes are joining the L2VNI</name>
            <t>When additional non-root nodes join the L2VNI by sending a
            (L2IID, their RLOCs, Multicast Group) Map-Register, the MapServer
            is storing new entries in the Vector of devices participating in
            the L2VNI. The MapServer then sends MAP-Notify to the nodes with a
            vector of RLOCs containing the Root node and the respective RLOCs
            of the joining devices. That means that means that at anytime, a
            new device joining the L2VNI will receive a list of root nodes plus
            its own RLOC confirming that it has successfully joined the L2VNI.
            The Root nodes are also notified that new members are joining the
            L2VNI through a Map-Notify containing a vector of all non-root RLOCs.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees_Tree-Formation">
            <name>Multicast Tree formation</name>
            <t>The Root Tree identities the new nodes and issue a PIM SSM Join
            towards them. The non-root nodes will initiate PIM SSM join the
            root nodes only. This results is a bi-directionnal multicast tree
            passing through the root node.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees_RootNode-Redundancy">
            <name>Root node redundancy</name>
            <t>Since the data traffic is passing through the root nodes it is
            critical to be able to provide redundancy to those nodes.
            If more than one root node has been registered in the L2VNI, the
            locator priority will be used to determined which one will receive
            the PIM Joins from the non-root nodes. The secondary root node will
            track the reachability of the primary root node in the RIB. When the
            primary node fails, the IGP will remove the RLOC for the RIB and
            make the LISP next-hop unreachable. This will trigger a new PIM
            Join to the secondary root node. At this point, the secondary root
            node will also detect that the primary root node is unavailable
            and will elect itself as the new primary root node. As candidate
            root node, it has also received a Vector of non-root nodes participating
            to the L2VNI and will trigger PIM SSM Joins towards them.
            The bidirectional multicast tree is rebuilt and BUM forwarding
            is restored. To prevent any interruptions by misconfigured root-nodes
            or failed primary root node coming back online, no pre-empt should
            be done when a new root node with a higher priority is added in the network.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering">
          <name>Traffic Steering</name>
          <t>In some situations, BUM transport is only required for IPv4 ARP
          and DHCP services to a gateway located outside of the fabric network.
          Such services require unidirectional BUM transport
          (ARP request and DHCP Discover) and the return traffic is unicast
          (ARP reply and DHCP Offer/Request/Ack). If the PxTR connected
          to the external gateway it should also be able to be configured
          as unidirectional root node for the L2VNI. That means that it should
          be able to receive BUM traffic from other non-root nodes and forward
          it outside of the fabric.</t>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering_Unidir-RootNode-Join">
            <name>A unidirectional root node is joining the L2VNI</name>
            <t>Similarly to <xref target="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees"/>, until the first root node is discovered the Map-Server
            will reject any other MAP-REGISTER. When a root node is configured to act
            as a unidirectional root node, it sends a MAP-REGISTER to the MAP-SERVER
            (L2IID, RLOC, Multicast Group) with two Flags (Root, Unidirectional).
            At this point, the MAP-Server is ready to receive non-root node MAP-Registers.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering_NonRootNode-Join">
            <name>Non-root nodes are joining the L2VNI</name>
            <t>When additional non-root nodes joins the L2VNI by sending
            a MAP-REGISTER (L2IID, RLOC, Multicast Group), the MS creates
            new entries in the DB. The MS sends a MAP-Notify back to the
            non-root nodes with their respective RLOC in the vector
            (like if they were the only node in the topology). The MS also
            sends a MAP-NOTIFY to the unidirectional root node with the
            list of new nodes in the topology.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering_Tree-Formation">
            <name>Multicast Tree formation</name>
            <t>After being notified by the MS, the unidirectional root node will
            initiate a PIM SSM Join towards the new non-root nodes to receive
            encapsulated BUM traffic from them. The non-root nodes are not aware
            of other nodes in the topology and will not initiate any PIM SSM join.
            This result of this is a unidirectional multicast tree where the
            xTR can send encapsulated BUM traffic to the PxTR. Since the return
            traffic is unicast, there is no needs to maintain multicast state
            in the underlay on non-root nodes.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering_RootNode-Redundancy">
            <name>Redundancy</name>
            <t>There are two parts that come into play when considering the redundancy
            of unidirectional root-nodes. The first part relates to the point <xref target="Optimisations_Bidir-Trees_RootNode-Redundancy"/>
            which remains almost the same except that the
            non-root nodes will not care about the switchover to another root node.
            When the primary root node fails, the secondary will detect it and issue
            a PIM SSM Join towards all the non-root to recreate a new multicast tree. </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="Optimisations_Traffic-Steering_RootNode-Types-Exclusion">
            <name>Coexistence with bidirectional root nodes</name>
            <t>Both types of root nodes (unidirectional and bidirectional)
            MUST NOT coexist in a given L2VNI.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This document should not affect the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
          <xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9300.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9301.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8378.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-lisp-eid-mobility-15.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>The authors want to thank Marc Portoles-Comeras and Alberto Rodriguez-Natal
        for their insightful contribution to shaping the ideas in this
        document.</t>
    </section>
 </back>
</rfc>